Guide to the Oscar Buneman Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Oscar Buneman papers
1913-1989
1941-1989
SC0450
Buneman, Oscar, 1913-
17 Linear feet
Research notes, papers, reprints, correspondence, lectures, and class materials from his teaching career and research while at Stanford University, with some materials from the 1940s and 1950s relevant to his work on magnetrons. Subjects include plasma physics, fourier transformations, Cray computers, and poisson solvers. Papers also include films of computer simulations, tetrahedron models, and one file of personal documents.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Ruth Buneman, 1993.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Oscar Buneman, prominent scientist in the fields of plasma electrodynamics, fundamental electromagetic theory, and numerical anaylsis, was Professor of Electrical Engineering at Stanford University from 1960 until he reached emeritus status in 1984. While at Stanford he worked on laboratory applications of plasma phys ics to cross-field microwave devices, stability analysis, and other phenomena. He also developed, with a series of collaborators, a three-dimensional electromagnetic particle simulation code (TRISTAN) for Cray supercomputers.
Buneman, born in Italy in 1913 to German parents, was imprisoned by the Nazis for political resistance in 1934. Upon his release in 1935, he went to Manchester University in England where he received his bachelor's, master's, and doctoral degrees in mathematics. He continued postdoctural work there on the magnetron. In 1944 he was a member of the British mission to the Manhattan project at Berkeley, Calfornia. From 1950 to 1960 he was a member of Peterhouse College, Cambridge.
Buneman died on January 24, 1993.
Description of the Collection
Research notes, papers, reprints, correspondence, lectures, and class materials from his teaching career and research while at Stanford University, with some materials from the 1940s and 1950s relevant to his work on magnetrons. Subjects include plasma physics, fourier transformations, Cray computers, and poisson solvers. Papers also include films of computer simulations, tetrahedron models, and one file of personal documents.
Access Terms
Buneman, Oscar, 1913-; Stanford University. Department of Electrical Engineering. Faculty.; Cray computers.; Fourier transformations.; Magnetrons.; Motion pictures; Plasma (Ionized gases).; Poisson's equation.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Poisson solver notes (Box 1)
  - Notes for London Conference, possibly on radiation of growing waves, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Misc. notes on magnetron, including 1989 correspondence (Box 1)
  - Papers on magnetron (Box 1)
  - Magnetron lecture (with other materials), 1941 (Box 2)
  - Magnetron lecture notes, Santa Fe meeting, 1981 (Box 2)
  - E- I Instability (Box 2)
  - Notes for book on Continuum Electrodynamics, ca. 1962 (Box 2)
  - Relativity notes (Box 2)
  - Continuum Electrodynamcis - manuscript (Box 2)
  - Papers on magnetron (Box 3)
  - Notes on FFT (Box 3)
  - Notes on FFT (Fast Fourier Transform?) (Box 4)
  - Notes on Hartley Transform (Box 4)
  - J.C. Slater's report on magnetron oscillator, 1941 (Box 4)
  - Diagnostic notes for Tristan; solar wind interaction for particles and fields (Box 4)
  - Old Tristan code notes (Box 5)
  - Notes on num. simulation of the Taylor-Green vortices, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Checkboard proposal (Box 5)
  - Personal papers (citizenship, marriage, etc.) (Box 5)
  - Notes and reprints related to conference on history of scientific and numeric computing, 1987 (Box 6)
  - Notes on Fast Fourier and Fast Hartley Transforms (Box 6)
  - Papers, print-outs, and correspondence (Box 6)
  - Papers and notes on Fast Fourier and Fast Hartley Transforms (Box 7)
  - CRAY programs, mover, etc. (Box 7)
  - CRAY programs, mover, etc. (Box 8)
  - CRAY programs, mover, etc. (Box 9)
  - Reprints on Tetrahedral Interpolatic, Hamiltonian Gas Dymanics, Plasma Physics, etc. (Box 9)
  - Reprints on plasma phys ics, poisson operators, computer simulations, crossed field devices, etc. (Box 10)
  - Reprints on curved field, waves in plasma, plasma physics, magnetron theory, etc. (Box 11)
  - Reprints on "Ribbon Bears", current-carrying plasma, air screw noise, etc. (Box 12)
  - Reprints on self-evident electrodynamics, continuum electrodynamics, circulation, particle accelerators, etc. (Box 13)
  - Misc. notes on radiation conditions, Poisson sol ver, errors and aliases due to interpolation of spectral (Box 14)
  - Patent (Box 14)
  - Misc. notes on radiation conditions, Poisson solver, errors and aliases due to interpolation of spectral data (Box 15)
  - Notes on work with students and associates (Box 15)
  - CAl (Box 15)
  - Correspondence (Box 15)
  - Notes on work with students and associates (Box 16)
  - NSR proposal (Box 16)
  - Starlab Seminar (Box 16)
  - Maltsev (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Owen Storey Misc. (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - CRAY Architecture and Assembl y Language (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Multiprocessors (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Global (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Scamp (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Relativistic Sheet Pinches with Current Shear (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - EE 288 (Box 18, Folder 1-12)
  - Collision Free Plasma Theory (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Longitudinal Oscillations (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - Effective Transport Coefficients (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - EE 354 (Box 18, Folder 16-23)
  - Helicon/Whistler Excitation (Box 18, Folder 24)
  - Introduction to Plasma Physics (Box 18, Folder 25)
  - Introduction to Plasma Physics (Box 18, Folder 26)
  - Problems and Solutions (Box 18, Folder 27)
  - EE 354 (Box 18, Folder 28)
  - EE 286 (Box 18, Folder 29-31)
  - Final, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - EE 356, Midterms, 1985 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Stress Tensor -Bennett (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Reson.2 dist. f'n (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Bernstein Disp. F'la (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Conductivities (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Whistler Signal Velocity (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Lower Hybrid Resonance (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Beam excitation of cyclotron resonance (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Self-consistent Mirror Configuration (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Problems relating to Chapter III (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Theta Pinch: earlier version (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Theta Pinch (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Piecewise Constant Field Mode l of Diode (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - l-D Debye Cloud (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Landau Without Complex Numbers (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Fluctuation Material (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - Plasma Magnetodynamis (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - Part III -Dynamics (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - Introduction to Plasma Physics (Box 20, Folder 1-5)
  - EE 292B (Box 20, Folder 6-24)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 20, Folder 25)
  - EE 271/272 (Box 20, Folder 26 -31)
  - Computer Printout (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - EE 288 (Box 21, Folder 2-17)
  - Effective Transport Coefficient (Box 21, Folder 18)
  - Transconductance of Stratified Medium Stream analysis (Box 21, Folder 19)
  - Split Orbits and Vascillating Orbits, 1966 Aug (Box 21, Folder 20)
  - EE 272: Final and Answer Sheet (Box 22, Folder 1-5)
  - EE 342: Problem Sets, Finals, and Answers (Folder 6-19)
  - EE 141 (Box 23, Folder 1-5)
  - EE 181 (Box 23, Folder 6-17)
  - Random Numbers: Do-It-Yourself and Better (Box 23, Folder 18)
  - EE 181 (Box 24, Folder 1-9)
  - CRAY Course (Box 24, Folder 10-18)
  - UNICOS User Command Ready Reference SQ-2056 5.0 (Box 25)
  - A Programmers Introduction to the IBM System/360... (Box 25)
  - UNICOS Primer SG-20l0 C (Box 25)
  - CRAY Computer Systems CFT77 Reference Manual (Box 25)
  - NCAR UNICOS Primer (Box 25)
  - Journal of Scientific Computing, 1986 (Box 26)
  - Siam Review, 1985 Dec - 1986 Sep (Box 26)
  - EE 261 (Box 26, Folder 1-16)
  - EE 261 (Box 27, Folder 1-32)
  - EE 261 (Box 28, Folder 1-12)
  - Autumn 82/83 Engineering Survey (Box 28, Folder 13)
  - Class List (Box 28, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 28, Folder 15)
  - EE 272 (Box 28, Folder 16-21)
  - EE 272 (Box 29, Folder 1-11)
  - EE 342 (Box 29, Folder 12)
  - Three (3) mailing Folders: "Radiation Course" (Box 29)
  - EE 272 (Box 30, Folder 1-6)
  - EE 288 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Radiation Course Class Notes (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Einstein Article (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Tetrahedron models (Box 31)
  - Films of computer simulations (Box 32)
  - Computer Space Plasma Physics: Simulation Techniques and Software, edited by H. Matsumoto and Y. Omura; includes software disk (Box 33)
  - Ruth Buneman, et.al ., "A Tribute to Oscar Buneman -Pioneer of Plasma Simulation," IEEE Transactions on Plasma Science, Vol. 22, No. 1 (xerox copy), 1994 Feb (Box 33)
  - Glass lantern slides of charts, tables, and equations (Box 34)
  - Glass lantern slides of charts, tables, and equations (Box 35)
  - Six photographs of geometric shapes (Box 35)
  - Unidentified video tape (Box 35)